this is a librivox recording all librivox recordings are in The public
domain for more information or to volunteer please visit librivox.org this recording by jay hall
the Wonderful Wizard of Oz by l frank Baum Chapter 10 The Guardian of the Gate
It was some time before the Cowardly Lion awakened, for he had lain among the
poppies a long while, breathing in their deadly fragrance; but when he did open
his eyes and roll off the truck he was very glad to find himself still alive. “I
ran as fast as I could,” he said, sitting down and yawning, “but the flowers were
too strong for me. How did you get me out?”
Then they told him of the field mice, and how they had generously saved him from
death; and the Cowardly Lion laughed, and said: “I have always thought myself a very
big and terrible; yet such little things as flowers came near to killing me, and
such small animals as mice have saved my life. How strange it all is! But, comrades,
what shall we do now?” “We must journey on until we find the road of yellow brick
again,” said Dorothy, “and then we can keep on to the Emerald City.” So, the Lion being
fully refreshed, and feeling quite himself again, they all started upon the
journey, greatly enjoying the walk through the soft, fresh grass; and it was
not long before they reached the road of yellow brick and turned again toward the
Emerald City where the Great Oz dwelt.
The road was smooth and well paved, now, and the country about was beautiful, so
that the travelers rejoiced in leaving the forest far behind, and with it the
many dangers they had met in its gloomy shades. Once more they could see fences
built beside the road; but these were painted green, and when they came to a
small house, in which a farmer evidently lived, that also was painted green. They
passed by several of these houses during the afternoon, and sometimes people came
to the doors and looked at them as if they would like to ask questions; but no
one came near them nor spoke to them because of the great Lion, of which they were very
afraid. The people were all dressed in a clothing of lovely emerald green color
and more peaked hats like those of the Munchkins. “This must be the Land of Oz,”
said Dorothy, “and we are surely getting near the Emerald City.” “Yes answer the
Scarecrow. “Everything is green here, while in the country of the Munchkins blue was
the favorite color. But the people do not seem to be as friendly as the Munchkins,
and I’m afraid we shall be unable to find a place to pass the night.” “I should
like something to eat besides fruit,” said the girl, “and I’m sure Toto is nearly
starved. Let us stop at the next house and talk to the people.” So, when they came
to a good-sized farmhouse, Dorothy walked boldly up to the door and knocked. A
woman opened it just far enough to look out, and said, “What do you want, child, and
why is that great Lion with you?” “We wish to pass the night with you, if you will
allow us,” answered Dorothy; “and the Lion is my friend and comrade, and would not
hurt you for the world.” “Is he tame as the woman, opening the door a little wider. “Oh,
yes,” said the girl, “and he is a great coward, too. He will be more afraid of you
than you are of him.” “Well,” said the woman, after thinking it over and taking
another peep at the Lion, “if that is the
case you may come in, and I will give you
some supper and a place to sleep.” So they all entered the house, where there were,
besides the woman, two children and a man.
The man had hurt his leg, and was lying on the couch in a corner. They seemed
greatly surprised to see so strange accompany and while the woman was busy
laying the table the man asked: “Where are you all going?” “To the Emerald City,”
said Dorothy, “to see the Great Oz.” “Oh, indeed!” exclaimed the man. “Are you sure
that Oz will see you?” “Why not?” she replied.
“Why, it is said that he never lets anyone come into his presence. I have been to
the Emerald City many times, and it is a beautiful and wonderful place; but I have
never been permitted to see the Great Oz, nor do I know of any living person who
has seen him.” “Does he never go out?” asked the Scarecrow.
“Never. He sits day after day in the great Throne Room of his Palace, and even those
who wait upon him do not see him face-to-face What is he like?” asked the girl. “That is
hard to tell,” said the man thoughtfully. “You see, Oz is
a Great Wizard, and he can take on any form he wishes. So that some say he looks
like a bird; and some say he looks like an elephant; and some say he looks like a
cat. To others he appears as a beautiful fairy, or a brownie, or any other form
that pleases him. But who the real Oz is, when is he in his own form, no living
person can tell.” “That is very strange,” said Dorothy, “but we must try, in some way,
to see him, or we shall have made our journey for nothing.” “Why do you wish to
see the terrible Oz?” asked the man. “I want him to give me some brains,” said the
Scarecrow eagerly. “Oh uh could do that easily enough,” declared the man. “He has
more brains than he needs.” “And I want him to give me a heart,” said the Tin Woodman.
“That will not trouble him,” continued the man, “for Oz has a large collection of
hearts, of all sizes and shapes.” “And I want him to give me courage,” said the Cowardly Lion
keeps a great pot of courage in his Throne Room,” said the man, “which he is
covered with a golden plate, to keep it from running over. He would be glad to
give you some.” “And I want him to send me back to Kansas,” said Dorothy. “Where is
Kansas?” asked the man, with surprised I don’t know,” replied Dorothy sorrowfully,
“but it is my home, and I’m sure it’s somewhere.” “Very likely. Well, Oz can do
anything; so I suppose he will find Kansas for you. But first you must get to
see him, and that will be a hard task; for the Great Wizard does not like to see
anyone, and he usually has his own way.
But what do YOU want?” he continued, speaking to Toto. Toto only wagged his
tail; for, strange to stay he could not speak. The woman now called to them that
supper was ready, so they gathered around the table and Dorothy ate some delicious
porridge and a dish of scrambled eggs and a plate of nice white bread, and
enjoyed her meal. The Lion ate some of the porridge, but did not care for it,
saying it was made from oats and oats were food for horses, not for
lions. The Scarecrow and the Tin Woodman ain't nothin at all.
Toto ate a little of everything, and was glad to get a good supper again. The
woman now gave Dorothy a bed to sleep in, and Toto lay down beside her, while the
Lion guarded the door of her room so she might not be disturbed.
The Scarecrow and the Tin Woodman stood up in a corner and kept quiet all night,
although of course they could not sleep.
The next morning, as soon as the sun was up, they started on their way, and soon
saw a beautiful green glow in the sky just before them. “That must be the
Emerald City,” said Dorothy. As they walked on, the green glow became brighter and
brighter, and it seemed that at last they were nearing the end of their travels.
Yet it was after noon before they came to the great wall that surrounded the
City. It was high and thick and of a bright green color. In front of them, and
at the end of the road of yellow brick, was a big gate, all studded with emeralds
that glittered so in the sun that even the painted eyes of the Scarecrow were
dazzled by their brilliancy. There was a bell beside the gate, and Dorothy pushed
the button and heard a silvery tinkle sound within. Then the big gate swung
slowly open, and they all passed through and found themselves in a high arched
room, the walls of which glistened with countless emeralds. Before them stood a
little man about the same size as the Munchkins. He was clothed all in green,
from his head to his feet, and even his skin was of a greenish tint and his side
was a large green box. When he saw Dorothy and her companions the man asked,
“What do you wish in the Emerald City?” “We came here to see the Great Oz,” said
Dorothy. The man was so surprised that this answer he sat down to think it over.
“It has been many years since anyone asked me to see Oz,” he said, shaking his
head in perplexity. “He is powerful and terrible, and if you come on an idle or
foolish errand to bother the wise reflections of the Great Wizard, he might
be angry and destroy you all in an instant.” “But it is not a foolish errand,
nor an idle one,” replied the Scarecrow; “it is important. And we have been told that
Oz is a good Wizard.” “So he is,” said the green man, “and he rules the Emerald City
wisely and well. But to those who are not honest, or who approach him from
curiosity, he is most terrible, and few have ever dared asked to see his face. I
am the Guardian of the Gates, and since you demand to see the Great Oz I must
take you to his Palace. But first you must put on the spectacle Why ask
Dorothy. “Because if you do not wear spectacles the brightness and glory of
the Emerald City would blind you. Even those who live in the City must wear
spectacles night and day. They are all locked on, for Oz so ordered it when the
City was first built, and I have the only key that will unlock them.” He opened the
big box, and Dorothy saw that it was filled with spectacles of every size and
shape. All of them had green glasses in them. The Guardian of the Gates found a
pair that would just fit Dorothy and put them over her eyes. There were two golden
bands fastened to them that passed around the back of her head, where they
were locked together by a little key that was at the end of a chain the
Guardian of the gate wore around his neck. When they were on, Dorothy could not
take them off had she wished, but of course she did not wish to be blinded by
the glare of the Emerald City, so she said nothing. Then the green man fitted
spectacles for the Scarecrow and the Tin Woodman and the Lion, and even on little
Toto; and all were locked fast with the key. Then the Guardian of the Gates put
on his own glasses and told them he was ready to show them to the Palace. Taking
a big golden key from a peg on the wall, he opened another gate, and they all
followed him through the portal into the streets of the Emerald City end of